4th Division "G".

Account of operations carried out by the 11th Brigade. April 9th - 16th inclusive.

APRIL 9TH

The march of the Brigade to the assembly areas was carried out without incident.

At 10 a.m. under orders received from the 4th Division the Brigade moved in column of route to the Old British Fron Line. The forward route was clear of Artillery which had advanced previously and the fire of only one gun had to be stopped.

After passing the Old British Front Line the Brigade advanced in two columns to the Blue Line, Units moving in column of route. Only very minor casualties were suffered and the Blue Line was reached ½ hour before the schedule time. At schedule time the Brigade moved in Artillery formation to assembly positions behind the Brown Line or 3rd German System. This advance (as that from the Old Front Line to the Blue Line) was made on a compass bearing and units reached their positions without difficulty. This phase was marked by a practically complete absence of Artillery fire by the Enemy and Battalions effected any slight adjustment in their frontages that were necessary without any interference on the part of the enemy.

At 3.10 p.m. the leading Battalions of the Brigade, 1st Somerset Light Infantry and 1st Hampshire Regiment passed through the 9th Division and advanced in Artillery formation until they came into view of the enemy in the 4th German System, when they deployed. The wire in front of this systement was found to be untouched by our Artillery fire and the only means of passing through it were the gaps which had been left in it by the enemy. The enemy offered on the whole, very little resistance, though some rifle and machine gun fire is reported. All the Germans with few exception in the Front Line surrendered, those in the Support Line fled Eastwards, many being shot down.

Meanwhile the 1st East Lancashire Regiment formed a defensive flank facing North from the POINT DU JOUR to the left of the Hampshire Regiment. Some bombing was necessary in the trenches in the vicinity of the POINT DU JOUR before the line could be established here, while the gunners in the German gun positions on the N.E. slope of the Spur appear to have offered a far more determined resistance.

In the advance of the two assaulting Battalions, direction had been lost with the result that the Brigade edged too much to the South and owing to the similarity of the ground and the roads passing through the German 4th System, the mistake was not realised till later, when it was rectified without nay difficulty.

The 1st Rifle Brigade crossed the Brown Line 25 minutes after the two assaulting Battalions. On reaching the wire in front of the 4th German System, the gaps of which were under hostile Artillery fire, some casualties were suffered. The SUNKEN ROAD appears to have been then as later the line of this hostile barrage and more casualties were sustained on this line.

The wire in front of HYDERABAD REDOUBT was uncut, but the German resistance was weak and the Redoubt was captured. The 1st Rifle Brigade immediately pushed forward patrols but encountered heavy Machine Gun and rifle fire and after an attempt to dig in posts, East of the Redoubt and further casualties had been sustained, it was determined to concentrate efforts on consolidating the Redoubt.

It is not quite certain what the troops of the enemy were who offered resistance at ths point and who dug in on a line 600 or 700 yds. East of the Redoubt. If they were the troops, who had retired from the 4th German System, they had recovered very quickly from their disorganisation. It is more probable that the retreating troops were rallied by fresh enemy troops who arrived on the scene about this time. These reserves, as also the enemy troops in their retreat from the 4th German System were subjected to a very heavy rifle and Machine Gun fire by our troops and it is certain that very severe casualties were inflicted on them. The Rifle Brigade expended so much ammunition on this that they had to cease fire to keep a reserve of ammunition. The Machine Gun Company report that they inflicted severe casualties on a Battalion of Infantry advancing in extended order on the GAVRELLE - ROEUX Road.

Before it was dark the enemy troops in this vicinity attempted a counter-attack on the Redoubt. This counter-attack was completely stopped by our Machine Gun fire and rifle fire from the 1st Rifle Brigade and 1st Hampshire Regiment, and many enemy dead were seen lying on the ground East of the Redoubt.

From this time onwards the situation became quieter as consolidation continued.

During the day the estimated number of prisoners taken was 350 Officers and other ranks of whom one was a General whose Head Quarters were in the SUNKEN ROAD. The number of guns captured including those subsequently discovered, was 26 of all calibres, of which 4 were 8" howitzers. In addition 8 Machine Guns and 1 Cooker, besides a large amount of warlike material of all descriptions.

APRIL 10TH

On the afternoon of the 10th instant, under orders received from the 4th Division, the 1st Somerset Light Infantry and 1st Hampshire Regiment sent out strong patrols to attempt to reach the line of the GAVRELLE - ROEUX Road. They were met with a very heavy Machine Gun and rifle fire though the Artillery fire was not so heavy. The two patrols of the 1st Somerset Light Infantry were unable to advance more than 100 or 200 yards and in a few minutes were practically all casualties; the platoons which were to have advanced in support and make good the GAVRELLE - ROEUX Road did not in consequence advance.

In the evening of the 10th instant, the enemy counter-attacked the 1st Hampshire Regiment who were occupying the 4th German system but did not press the attack home in the face of our Artillery and Machine Gun barrage. This was probably a reconnaissance in force. The 1st Hampshire Regiment sustained considerable casualties from enemy Artillery fire.

APRIL 11TH

The Brigade was ordered to form a defensive flank facing North to support an attack by the 10th and 12th Brigade, whose objective was GREENLAND HILL and PLOUVAIN.

The attack started at 12 noon and for some time it seemed as if the right of the 10th Brigade might reach the GAVRELLE - ROEUX Road. The attack however was held up by Machine Gun fire. The 1st Somerset Light Infantry who were detailed to form the defensive flank were unable to advance far and suffered heavy casualties from Machine Guns reported to be North and N.W. of the INN. During the attack Cavalry patrols attempted to emerge from FAMPOUX; of those that were seen all became casualties within two or three minutes.

At 5.0 p.m. the 1st Hampshire Regiment was ordered to bomb up the 4th German System as far as HONEY TRENCH. This operation was successful, though attended with considerable losses for so small an operation.

In the evening of the 11th and night 11th/12th the 1st East Lancashire Regimkent advanced their posts about 400 yards, thus pushing in front of several guns that had been abandoned by the enemy.

APRIL 12TH

The attack which had failed on the previous day was repeated by the 9th Division attacking, while the 1st Rifle Brigade supported the left flank of the attack. In order to assist this operation the 1st Hampshire Regiment were ordered to bomb up to the 4th German System as far as H.6.a.4.1. if possible. This minor operation started at 1.30 p.m, was unsuccessful mainly owing to rifle and Machine Gun fire. The main attack, which was supported by a heavier Artillery barrage than that of the 11th inst., started at 5.30 p.m. but was unsuccessful. The failure of the attack was again largely due to the enemy Machine Gun fire partly assisted by the fact that the 9th Division advanced in open order from the 4th German System (some 1000 yards behind our Front Line) and suffered very heavy casualties before Zero hour, besides giving the enemy warning of the attack.

The Rifle Brigade were caught by flank and frontal Machine Gun fire and did not advance more that 100 - 200 yards. In this short distance they suffered severe casualties - 2 Officers and 51 O.Rs.

APRIL 13TH

No operation was carried out. During the night the enemy sent over a large number of gas shells - mainly on the Battery position of the 32nd Brigade, but a considerable number fell in EFFIE TRENCH in which the Support Company of the 1st East Lancashire Regiment was accommodated. 5 Gas casualties were sustained but none were serious.

APRIL 14TH

On the night of the 14th/15th the 1st East Lancashire Regiment advanced their posts to a line approximately B.29.d.1.1. - H.5.b.3.7. - HONEY TRENCH. They were also instructed to reconnoitre and occupy the dugouts in H.5.d.8.6 A report was received that these had been reconnoitred and found abandoned but this was later found to be untrue.

APRIL 15TH

At 6.30 p.m. after a 3½ hours bombardment by Heavy Artillery the 1st Hampshire Regiment attempted to work up the 4th German system as far as H.6.a.4.1., under cover of a creeping barrage of 4.5 howitzers, advancing at a rate of 100 yards in 6 minutes. The attempt was unsuccessful, the men being unable to advance owing to rifle and Machine Gun fire from both flanks.

Judging after the event, it seems probable that the Heavy Artillery bombardment had been too long and that the trenches were so damaged that our men in advancing had to expose themselves to enemy Machine Gun and rifle fire, while moving over the damaged portions of the trench.

APRIL 16TH

The Brigade was relieved in the line night of the 16th/17th and moved to the Railway cutting and Black Line.

Judging by the operations as a whole the following deductions may be drawn :-

1.  It might have been possible, by the immediate use of Cavalry to exploit the success of the 9th instant.

2.  Once the enemy had recovered from the effect of our rapid advance by the assistance of fresh troops hurried to the spot, the chance of converting the operations into "Open Warfare" had gone. The chance had gone, probably, as early as dusk on the evening of the 9th instant and this was proved by the failure of the patrols of the 1st Somerset Light Infantry and even more certainly by the failure of the attack of the 10th and 12th Brigades on the 11th instant. It would seem that once the enemy has recovered from the demoralisation of a rapid retreat and has time to get his Machine Guns into action, the only course to be adopted is to renew the Artillery preparation. This takes time, as his Machine Guns and Strong Points must be located by careful reconnaissance and knocked out.

3.  It is for all practical purposes impossible to cut wire with 60 pdrs. without direct observation. The wire in front of the 3rd German System, in the condition in which it was, when our attacking troops reached it, would have held up the attack had there been any but demoralised troops behind it. The wire in front of the 4th German System and HYDERABAD REDOUBT was untouched.

4.  In the three operations since the 9th, carried out by this Brigade, it has been the Machine Guns that have held up our men. The enemy's Artillery barrage could not have done this. Our Artillery should therefore be almost entirely concentrated on knocking out the enemy's Machine Guns.

17th April, 1917.

S E C R E T

11th Inf. Bde. No. BM 4/194.

4th Division "G".

Reference your G.671 of the 20th instant. The following is an account of the operations of the 11th April, 1917 :-

1.  Early on the morning of the 11th inst., orders were received that the 4th Division was to advance and take up a line PLOUVAIN - GREENLAND HILL - INN I.7.a.2.8. - HYDERABAD REDOUBT. The order of the Brigades from North to South was 11th, 10th and 12th.

The objectives were as follows :-

1st OBJECTIVE. ROUX - GAVRELLE Road as far North as the INN at I.7.a.2.8., with a defensive flank from the INN to HYDERABAD REDOUBT.

2nd OBJECTIVE. PLOUVAIN - GREENLAND HILL, with a defensive flank from I.7.b.2.8. to the INN.

2.  The role of the 11th Brigade was to support the left flank of the 4th Division, forming a defensive flank in the first objective from the INN at I.7.a.2.8 to HYDERABAD REDOUBT, and in the second objective from I.7.b.2.8 to the INN.

The boundary between the 11th and 10th Brigades was a line HYDERABAD REDOUBT (inclusive to the 11th Brigade) to Cross Roads I.7.a.4.3. - I.7.b.2.8.

3.  The 1st Somerset Light Infantry were detailed to support the attack of the 10th and 12th Brigades and to form the defensive flank from HYDERABAD REDOUBT to the INN at I.7.a.2.8. later to I.7.b.2.8. Their attack was to be covered by machine gun fire from the 11th Machine Gun Coy., which was mainly directed against the ground in H.6.d. and I.1.c., where machine guns had been located on the previous day.

Their attack was also to be supported by Lewis Gun and rifle fire by the 1st Hampshire Regiment from HAZARD TRENCH.

Zero Hour was fixed at 12 noon.

4.  For the operation, 11th Brigade Battle Head Quarters were established in the dugouts in the SUNKEN ROAD at H.11.c.8.3., while the Head quarters of the 1st Somerset Light Infantry were established in HYDERABAD REDOUBT. From both places good observation of the operations was obtained.

5.  The attack started at 12 noon. Our Artillery barrage appeared to be fairly thick but was not so dense as that on the 12th instant.

The enemy at once opened a heavy machine gun fire and after the lapse of a few minutes put down an Artillery barrage. (1) on or about our Front Line through HYDERABAD REDOUBT. (2) on the SUNKEN ROAD in H11.c.

From the SUNKEN ROAD, the movements of the 10th and 11th Brigades could be seen and they advanced for about 200 or 300 yards suffering heavy casualties. On the South in H.18.a. and b., they may have advanced some 500 to 600 yards but the smoke made accurate observation difficult. Beyond this point troops appeared unable to get forward and the leading lines were mown down. (Afterwards, when the smoke cleared, the dead of the 2nd Seaforths could be observed lying in rows in front of the German line). In particular a strong point about H.12.d.9.9. was strongly held by Germans and many of our dead could be seen lying 200 - 300 yards to the West of it.

The 1st Somerset Light Infantry attacked on a one-Company front and they report that they had difficulty in moving out of HYDERABAD REDOUBT owing to the depth of the trenches and the fact that they were crowded out by the 10th Brigade. They do not appear to have got beyond a N. & S. line through H.12.c.7.8. They could not advance beyond this line owing to the heavy machine gun fire. Some of them got in the communication trench which runs Eastward from HYDERABAD REDOUBT and attempted to bomb towards the enemy but were stopped by machine gun fire as the trench was shallow.

They dug in on this line making a block in the communications trench running East from the REDOUBT about H.12.c.7.8. and also dug in posts East of the HYDERABAD REDOUBT to about H.12.a.0.4.

The casualties suffered by the 1st Somerset Light Infantry on this day were, Officers 3, Other Ranks 20.

6.  There was no question of them coming back from any objective as they never got beyond a line 200 - 300 yards West of the German trench.

As far as could be observed, the 10th Brigade did not reach the German trench which ran parallel to and about 300 yards West of the GAVRELLE - ROUEX Road.

21/4/17. (Signed) Brigadier General. Commanding 11th Infantry Brigade.

War Diary – 11 Inf Bde, Vol 28

April 1917

Place

|

Date

|

Hour

|

Summary of Events and Information

|

Remarks

Bde. Hd. Qrs

Dieval

|

1.

|

|

Brigade in training

|

|

2.

|

|

Brigade in training

|

|

3.

|

|

Brigade in training

|

|

4.

|

|

Brigade in training

|

|

5.

|

|

Brigade in training

|

Hermaville

|

6.

|

|

11th Brigade group plus 11th Field Ambulance & No 3 Coy 4th Divisional Train, marched to HAUTE AVESNES area. This move marked the commencement of the Brigade moving up to Battle.

|

See, Operation Order No: 80

Hermaville

|

7.

|

|

Brigade at rest in HAUTE AVESNES area.

|

Ref Map 1/100,000 Lens Sheet

Maroeuil

|

8.

|

|

11th Brigade moved to MAROEUIL – MAROEUIL WOOD area. The 526th Durham Field Coy R.E. Came under orders of the B.G.C., 11th Brigade at 7 p.m.

|

See Op. Order No 82.

Ref Map 1/100,000 Lens, 1/20,000 51CNE France

Bde Hd Qrs in action

|

9.

|

|

The following is an account of the operations from the 9th to the 16th inclusive. The 11th Infantry Brigade less the 11th Field Ambulance & No 3 Coy 4th Divisional Train left MAROEUIL at 5.30 a.m. For the Assembly areas preparatory to the attack. See 11th Brigade Instruction No 6 appendix C & D issued with Op order No 80.

Ref Maps. 1/20,000 51C NW, 51C NE

1/10,000 ARRAS 51B NW3

1/10,000 FAMPOUX 51B NW4

Throughout the account of operations Map “A” issued with 11th Brigade Instructions No 2 attached to Op order No 79, should be perused.

Zero hour for the attack was 5.30 am

The Brigade was timed not to leave the assembly areas until zero plus 4 hours. (see appendix D accompanying 11th Brigade instructions No 6 & Time Table of Infantry Advances, appendix A issued with 11th Brigade Instructions No 2 of Op order No 79)

Before going further into the Brigades movements it is necessary to explain briefly operations which were to take place by the 9th Division previous to the Brigade coming into action.

The 9th Division front stretch from the river SCARPE to G.6.d.0.2 (ref: map ARRAS 51B NW3). From G.6.d.0.2 a straight line from LE POINT DU JOUR in H.3.b.2.2 marks the left boundary of this Division. The river SCARPE the right boundary.

The 27th Brigade was on the left, the South African Brigade in the centre, the 26th Brigade on the right.

The first objective of the 9th Division was the 1st German System of trenches termed The BLACK LINE. The 2nd objective the Railway Embankment termed The BLUE LINE. The third objective, The 3rd German System, a line roughly from the POINT DU JOUR to H.15.a.30, termed the BROWN LINE.

The 4th Division was responsible for the capture of the 4th objective, a line from the POINT DU JOUR to H.12.a.4.0 to H.18.d.2.0 termed The GREEN LINE; this includes part of the 4th German System and the HYDERABAD REDOUBT, a distance of 6000 yards from the British Front Line and of 9½ miles about from MAROEUIL.

The 4th Division followed the 9th Division, but attacked with 2 Brigades only. The 11th Brigade on the left, the 12th on the right, & the 10th in reserve. For Brigade boundaries, objectives & routes see Map “A” & 11th Brigade Instructions no 2 issued with Op order 79.

The march of the Brigade from MAROEUIL to the Assembly Areas was carried out with incident. The 4th Division upon receiving news of the capture of the BLUE LINE, at 10 am ordered the 11th Brigade to move. The Brigade moved in column of route to the old British Front Line. The forward route was clear of artillery which had advanced previously & the fire of only one Gun had to be stopped.

After passing the old British Front Line the Brigade advanced in two columns to the BLUE LINE, units moving in columns of route. Only very minor casualties were suffered and the BLUE LINE was reached in ½ an hour before schedule time.

At schedule time (see table of Infantry Advances Appendix A issued with 11th Brigade instruction No 2.) the Brigade moved in artillery formations to assembly positions behind The BROWN LINE on 3rd German System. The advance was made on a compass bearing & units reached their positions without difficulty. This phase was marked by a practically complete absence of artillery fire by the enemy & battalions effected ant slight adjustments in their frontages that were necessary without any interference on part of the enemy.

At 3.10 pm the leading battalions of the Brigade, 1/Somerset Light Infantry and 1/Hampshire Regiment, passed through the 9th Division and advanced in artillery formation until they came within view of the enemy within the 4th German System, when they deployed. The wire in front of this system was found to be untouched by our artillery fire and the only means of passing through it was by the gaps which had been left in it by the enemy. The enemy offered on the whole little resistance, though some rifle & machine gun fire is reported. All the Germans with few exceptions in the front line surrendered. Those in the support line fled Eastwards, many being shot down. Meanwhile the 1/East Lancashire Regt formed up a defensive flank facing North from the POINT DU JOUR to the left of the 1/Hampshire Regt. Some bombing was necessary in the trenches in the vicinity of the POINT DU JOUR before the line could be established here, while the gunners in the German Gun positions on the N.E. slope of the spur appear to have offered a far more determined resistance. The advance of the two assaulting battalions direction had been lost with the result that the brigade edged too much to the South and owing to the similarity of the ground & the roads passing through the 4th German System, the mistake was not realized till later, when it was rectified without any difficulty.

The 1st Rifle Brigade crossed the BROWN LINE 25 minutes after the two assaulting battalions, on reaching the wire in front of the 4th German System, the gaps of which were under hostile artillery fire, some casualties were suffered, The sunken road appears to have been then as later the line of the hostile barrage and most casualties were sustained on this line.

The wire in front of the HYDERABAD REDOUBT was uncut, but the German resistance was weak and the redoubt was captured. The 1/Rifle Brigade immediately pushed forward patrols but encountered heavy machine gun fire and after an attempt to dig in posts East of the redoubt and further casualties had been sustained it was determined to consolidate efforts on consolidating the redoubt.

It is not quite certain what the troops of the enemy were who offered resistance at this point and who dug in on a line 600 or 700x East of the Redoubt. If they were the troops who had retired from the 4th German System, they had recovered very quickly from their disorganization. It is more probable that retiring troops were rallied by the fresh Enemy troops who arrived on the scene about this time. There reserves as also the enemy troops in their retreat from the 4th German System were subjected to very heavy rifle & machine gun fire by our troops & it is certain that very severe casualties were inflicted on them. The Rifle Brigade expended so much ammunition on this that they had to cease fire to keep a reserve of ammunition. The Machine Gun Company report that they inflicted severe casualties on a battalion of infantry advancing in extended order on the GAVRELLE – ROUEUX road. Before it was dark the enemy troops in this vicinity attempted a counter attack on the redoubt, this attack was completely stopped by our machine gun & rifle fire from the 1/Rifle Brigade and 1/Hampshire Regt., and many Enemy dead were seen lying on the ground East of the Redoubt. From this time onward the situation became quieter and consolidation was continued. During the day the estimated number of prisoners taken was 350 officers & other ranks of whom one was a General whose headquarters were in the SUNKEN ROAD. The number of Guns captured including those subsequently discovered was 26 of all calibres of which 4 were 8” howitzers. In addition 8 machine guns and one cooker besides a large amount of warlike material of all descriptions.

The casualties of the Brigade were – (see 11th Brigade Casualty Report from 9th to 20th April 1917)

|

See 11th Brigade Instruction No 2

|

10.

|

|

On the afternoon of the 10th inst under orders received from the Division the 1/Somerset L.I. & 1/Hampshire Regt sent out strong patrols to attempt to reach the line of the GAVRELLE – ROEUX road. They were met with a very heavy machine gun & rifle fire though their artillery fire was not so heavy. The two patrols of the 1/Somerset LI were unable to advance more that 100 or 200 yards and in a few minutes were practically all casualties, the platoons which were to advanced in support & make good the GAVERELLE-ROEUX road did not in consequence advance. In the evening of the 10th inst the enemy counter attacked the 1/Hampshire Regt who were occupying the 4th German System but did not push the attack home in the face of our artillery & machine gun barrage. This was probably a reconnaissance in force. The 1/Hampshire Regt sustained considerable losses from enemy artillery fire.

Casualties - (see 11th Brigade Casualty Report 9th to 20th April 1917)

|

|

11.

|

|

The Brigade was ordered to form a defensive flank facing North tp support ab attack by the 10th & 12th Brigade, whose objective was GREENLAND HILL and PLOUVAIN. The attack started at 12 noon and for sometime it seemed as if the right of the 10th Brigade might reach the GAVRELLE – ROEUX road. The attack however was held up by machine gun fire. The 1/Somerset LI who were detailed to form the defensive flank were unable to advance far and suffered heavy casualties from machine guns reported to N & NW of the Inn.

|

I.7.d.3.8

ref ARRAS 1/10,000

|

|

|

During the attack Cavalry patrols attempted to emerge from FAMPOUX; of those that were seen all became casualties within two or three minutes.

|

|

|

|

At 5 pm the 1/Hampshire Regt was ordered to bomb up the 4th German System as far as HONEY TRENCH. This operation was successful, though attended with considerable losses for so small an operation. In the evening of the 11th & night 11/12 yjr 1/East Lancashire Regt advanced their posts about 400 yds, thus pushing in front of several Guns that had been abandoned by the enemy. Casualties – (see list as before)

|

H.11.d

ref ARRAS 1/10,000

|

12.

|

|

The attack which had failed on the previous day, was repeated by the 9th Division attacking while the 1st Rifle Brigade supported the left flank of the attack. In order to assist this operation the 1/Hampshire Regt was ordered to bomb up the 4th German System as far as H.6.a.4.1 if possible. This minor operation started at 1.30 pm but was unsuccessful mainly owing to rifle & machine gun fire. The main attack which was supported by a heavier artillery barrage than that of the 11th inst started at 5.30 pm, but was unsuccessful. The failure of the attack was again due to the enemy machine gun fire partly assisted by the fact that the 9th Division advanced in open order from the 4th German System (some 1000 yds behind our front line) and suffered very heavy casualties before zero hour, besides giving the enemy warning of the attack, The Rifle Brigade were caught by flank & frontal machine gun fire and did not advance more than 100 to 200 yds. In this short distance they suffered severe casualties 2 officers, 51 OR. Casualties, (see list as before)

|

ARRAS sheet 1/10,000

|

13.

|

|

No operation was carried out. During the night the enemy sent over a large number gas shells mainly on the battery positions of the 32nd Bde but a considerable number fell on EFFIE TRENCH in which the support Company of the 1st East Lancashire Regt was accommodated. Five gas casualties were sustained, but none were serious. Casualties (see list as before)

|

Communication trench from 3rd to 4th German system.

|

14.

|

|

On the night of the 14th/15th the 1/East Lancashire Regt advanced their posts to a line approx: B.29.d.1.1 – H.5.b.3.7 – HONEY TRENCH, they were also instructed to reconnoitre & occupy the dug-outs in H.5.d.8.6. A report was received that these had been reconnoitred and found abandoned bu this was later found to be untrue. Casualties (see list as before)

|

FAMPOUX sheet 1/10,000

ARRAS sheet 51BNW3 1/10,000

|

15.

|

|

At 6.30 pm after a 3½ hours bombardment by heavy artillery the 1/Hampshire Regt attempted to work up the 4th German System as far as H.6.a.4.1 under cover of a creeping barrage of 4.5 hows. Advancing at a rate of 100 yds in 6 minutes. The attempt was unsuccessful, the men being unable to advance owing to rifle & machine gun fire from both flanks. Judging after the event it seems probable that the heavy artillery bombardment had been too long and that the trenches were so damaged that our own men in advancing had to expose themselves to enemy machine gun & rifle fire while moving over the damaged portions of the trench. Casualties – (see list as before)

|

|

16.

|

|

The Brigade was relieved in the line of the night 16/17 & moved to the Railway Cutting (BLUE LINE) and the BLACK LINE.

Judging the operation as a whole the following deductions may be drawn

(1) It might have been possible by the immediate use of cavalry to exploit the success of the 9th inst.

(2) Once the enemy had recovered from the effect of our rapid advance, by the assistance of fresh troops hurried to the stop the chance of converting the operation into “Open Warfare” had gone. The chance had gone probably as early as dusk on the evening of the 9th inst and this was proved by the failure of patrols of the 1/Somerset LI & even more certainly by the failure of the attack of the 10th & 12th Brigades on the 11th inst. It would seem that once the enemy has recovered from the demoralisation of a rapid retreat and has time to get his machine guns into action, the only course to be adopted is to renew the artillery preparation. This takes time, as his machine guns & strong points must be located by careful reconnaissance and knocked out.

(3) It is for all practical purposes impossible to cut wire with 60 pounders, without direct observation. The wire in front of the 3rd German System, in the condition in which it was, when our attacking troops reached it, would have held up the attack had there been any but demoralised troops behind it. The wire in front of the 4th German System and HYDERABAD REDOUBT was untouched.

(4) In the three operations since the 9th carried out by this brigade, it has been the machine guns that have held up our men. The enemy's artillery barrage could not have done this. Our artillery should therefore be almost entirely concentrated on knocking out the enemies machine guns.

|

Relief by 10th Brigade

BLUE LINE

|

17.

|

|

The 11th Brigade Group less the 11th Field Ambulance & No 5 Coy Train moved with the reserve and was accommodated in dug-outs & trench shelters in the BLUE & BLACK LINE as follows.

BLUE LINE

Brigade H.Q.

1/East Lancashire Regt

1/Hampshire Regt

11th Machine Gun Coy

11th Trench Mortar Battery

BLACK LINE

1/Somerset Light Infantry

1/Rifle Brigade

|

BLUE LINE

|

18.

|

|

The 11th Brigade was in reserve on the 17th. Orders were received from the 4th Division for the 11th Brigade to relieve the 12th Brigade in the old British Support line. In the evening the 1/East Lancashire Regt. moved back to the old British support line and took billets from the 2nd Essex Regt who moved up to the BLUE LINE.

|

See Op order No 83

|

19.

|

|

The order for the 12th Brigade to relieve the 11th was cancelled & the 11th Brigade remained in the BLUE & BLACK LINES with the exception of the 1/East Lancashire Regt who had moved on the 18th. The 4th Division was ordered to hold itself in readiness to proceed out of the forward area on being relieved by the 37th Division.

|

Agnes-Les-Duisans

|

20.

|

|

The 11th Brigade was relieved by the 111th Brigade & received orders to proceed to AGNES-LES-DUISANS area. The 1st line transport & call personnel that were left behind with the transport at the beginning of operations rejoined their units. The 11th Brigade including the 11th Field Ambulance & No 3 Coy Train billeted in AGNES-LESA-DUISANS in the evening. Although the men had come straight out of the reserve line, there were only two or three cases of men falling out on the march which was about 8 miles. (See Op order No 84, Ref Map 1/100,000 Lens sheet)

|

Ref Map 1/100,000 Lens sheet

Bde Hd Qrs

IZEL-LES-HAMEAU

|

21.

|

|

Orders were received from the 4th Division for the 11th Brigade to proceed to IZEL-LES-HAMEAU area. The brigade group arrived in this area in the afternoon and billeted as follows.

IZEL-LES-HAMEAU

Brigade H.Q.

1/Somerset Light Infantry

1/East Lancashire Regt

1/Hampshire Regt

VILLERS-SUR-SIMON

1/Rifle Brigade

AMBRINES

11th Machine Gun Coy

LES HAMEAU

11th Trench Mortar Battery

|

See Op order No 85.

Ref Map 1/100,000 Lens sheet

|

22.

|

|

11th Brigade Group at rest.

|

|

23.

|

|

11th Brigade Group at rest.

|

|

24.

|

|

11th Brigade Group training.

|

|

25.

|

|

11th Brigade Group training.

|

|

26.

|

|

11th Brigade Group training.

|

|

27.

|

|

11th Brigade in training.

|

FREVIN-CAPELLE

|

28.

|

|

Orders were received from 4th Division for the 11th Brigade to proceed to FREVIN-CAPELLE area. The move took place in the morning.

Owing to the accommodation falling short of that slated in Oper. order No 86 units billeted in the following places.

FREVIN-CAPELLE

Brigade H.Q.

1/Hampshire Regt

526th Durham Field Coy R.E.

CAPELLE-FERMONT

1/East Lancashire Regt

Huts E.17.c central

1/Somerset Light Infantry

1/Rifle Brigade

Huts E.17.a central

11th Machine Gun Coy

11th Trench Mortar Battery

ACQ

No 3 Coy Train

Ref: Map 51C 1/40,000

|

See Op order No 86

Y HUTS

|

29.

|

|

Orders were received from 4th Division for the 11th Brigade Group less the 11th Field Ambulance & No3 Coy Train to proceed to “Y HUTS”. This move was carried out in the morning. The weather was very warm & bright. “Y” Huts are situation on the main ARRAS – ST POL road, L1b & L2c.

|

Ref Map 1/40,000 FRANCE 51C

|

30.

|

|

Orders were received from the 4th Division for the 11th infantry Brigade to proceed to ARRAS and take over billets of the 10th Inf Brigade. The move was carried out during the day. The 10th & 12th Brigades moved up to take over the line from the 34th Division; the 11th Brigade was in reserve. The line being taken over by the 10th & 12th Brigades was roughly I.7 central, I.13 central, I.19 central. This marks the second entry of the 4th Division on to the front they captured & defended from April 9th 1917.

|

Ref Map 1/20,000 51BNW France

11th Inf. Bde. No. BM 63/292.

11th Infantry Brigade - Daily Intelligence Summary

15/8/17 - 16/8/17

OPERATIONS

Our own

A standing patrol was out from 12 midnight until 3.45 a.m. 30 yds. in front of our line between BIT LANE and T Sap. Nothing of importance was noticed.

Enemy

A hostile patrol was heard about 20 yds. from W Sap about 1 a.m. Lewis Gun fire was opened on it.

ARTILLERY

Enemy

200 5.9 shells were fired on to the road about pt. H.28.c.3.3. between 2.30 and 5.30 p.m. yesterday. 18 of which were blinds. The enemy was apparently shelling what he took to be a battery position. No casualties occurred.

Enemy granatenwerfer were active between 12 midnight and 3 a.m.

TRENCH MORTARS

Our Own

During the night the following points were fired on by our Stokes Mortars.

1. Salvoes on enemy wire at I.32.c.20.40.

2. Bursts of intense fire on enemy front line I.31.b.95.60 to I.32.c.05.25.

3. Machine Gun emplacement at I.31.b.80.70.

Enemy front line at I.25.b.75.40. to I.31.b.50.80.

Enemy

The enemy retaliated slightly for our fire on his front line. When firing on his front line from I.31.b.95.65. to I.32.c.05.25 Claret lights were put up from the front line but as far as could be ascertained nothing happened.

Bombarded our front line South of the River at intervals during the night, the last shoot taking place at 4.45 a.m.

INTELLIGENCE

About 5 a.m. 2 enemy light trench mortars were observed firing from about the junction of GRENADE TRENCH with BIT LANE (I.32.d.15.80.)

An Officer examined our wire from BIT LANE to junction of RIFLE and CHAIN Trenches. The wire is rather weak and out in places especially across BIT LANE and on the left of the front inspected. In most places the entanglement consists of thin strands of barbed wire and trip wire. There is some concertina wire (French).

16th August, 1917. (Signed) For B.G.C., 11th Infantry Brigade.

11th Inf. Bde. No. BM 63/317.

11th Infantry Brigade - Daily Intelligence Summary

16/8/17 - 17/8/17

OPERATIONS

Our own

A patrol went out at midnight from X Sap and worked along in front of our wire returning via W Sap.

Another patrol went out at 1 a.m. with a view to reconnoitering the wire in front of DEVILS TRENCH but had to return owing to the enemy's activity with rifle grenades and T.M's at this hour.

A standing patrol under an Officer was out all noght about 30 yds. in front of our wire at I.32/2. An N.C.O. and 2 men crept forward towards the enemy's lines. A Very light was fired from a shell hole about I.31.b.95.10. The enemy was also observed working on his wire in front of DEVILS TRENCH about I.32.a.2.3. with a covering party in front.

An Officers patrol went out at 1.30 a.m. and worked along below the top bank on the E side of the ravine to a point about 60 yds. from E Sap. A Machine Gun was seen to fire from the N end of ARCHIE TRENCH about I.25.d.4.8. They also heard the Machine Gunner cough and work his crank handle and the sound of digging was heard from this point. The patrol returned at 3.0 a.m.

An Officers patrol went out at 9.15 p.m. from N. end of FINGER. No forward posts were occupied by the enemy but the grass showed many tracks. A Machine Gun appeard by the sound to fire from a position at the edge of the lake at I.25.b.1.1.

An Officers patrol lefy Y Sap at midnight. They proceeded about 60 yds. along HARNESS LANE and then N along ANGEL about 50 yds. outside the enemy wire. Nothing was seen or heard.

ARTILLERY

Enemy

Very quiet. At 8.0 a.m. 10 rounds of 4.2 in. fell around B Sap. Both yesterday morning and at 4.0 a.m. this morning about 8 to 10 rounds fell between BAYONET and WELFORD S. of JOHNSON. HIMALAYA was shelled several times during the day.

During our bombardment between 1.15 a.m. and 1.45 a.m. the enemy retaliated on our right Coy with medium Trench Mortars and 4.2 on our front and support lines. It would appear that when green lights were sent up the range was lengthened. A T.M. about I.32.d.15.80. was again active. A T.M. was also firing from about I.32.c.8.3.

G Post was heavily shelled with 5.9 Hows. betweet 2.30 p.m. and 3 p.m. yesterday afternoon. The trench at pt. H.36.d.2.5. was blown in.

Machine Guns on our left flank report. enemy artillery very quiet on the whole. At 10 a.m. and 10.30 a.m. aerial torpedoes landed in ROEUX Village. at 5.30 a.m. two more aerial torpedoes landed in ROEUX WOOD near the river bank.

MACHINE GUNS

Our Own

Our M.G's at G, H and Orchard position fired on enemy tracks and roads between the followong hours. 10 - 10.30 p.m., 11.30 p.m. - 12 m/n., 1 a.m. to 2 a.m. Target - tracks between N. end of SACK WOOD and I.26.d.6.5.

Enemy

Enemy M.G's swept periodically during the night the vicinity of G and H Posts. Long range - unlocated.

Enemy M.G's traversed ELBOW and FINGER at intervals during the night, also WELFORD at intervals about 9.0 and 11 p.m. Very active after midnight.

Machine Guns on our left flank report. Enemy M.G. fire below normal. Gun on South bank of river was very active from 9.30 p.m. to 11.30 p.m. and again at 3 a.m. to 4 a.m. Gun firing from HAUSA WOOD direction, only opened up about 3 times at 10 p.m.

TRENCH MORTARS

Our Own

During the night shoots were carried out on ANGEL, DEVILS and ARCHIE Trenches.

Enemy

Retaliation was given by T.M's for our fire but was eventually silenced by us.

INTELLIGENCE

A 2.30 p.m. a white dog was seen at I.31.b.8.7. for a few seconds and quickly disappeared into enemy Sap. Voices were distinctly head calling to it. At 3.15 p.m. a dog was again seen in the same place, it was fired at but not hit, it disappeared into the enemy Sap.

At 3.0 p.m. a terrier with two puppies was seen at I.25.d.4.9. They disappeared into a dugout.

Our M.G's fired short bursts during the night. An enemy gun appeared to fire from I.31.b.95.10 and was probably involved in covering the wiring party mentioned above.

This morning between 4.45 a.m. and 5.15 a.m. enemy kite balloon over JIGSAW WOOD was observed signalling with a daylight lamp. At the same time the enemy fired 4 white rockets bursting into two white stars from the junction of DEVILS TRENCH and BIT LANE ending up with one green light. Immediately after this the enemy fired 4 salvoes from field guns at the area between the front line and MONCHY.

Aircraft

Between 4.0 and 6.0 p.m. E.A. were very active over our lines; they were dispersed by our own machines and M.G. fire and also A.A. fire.

17th August, 1917. (Signed) For B.G.C., 11th Infantry Brigade.

Supplementary Intelligence Summary

Report from O.C. 1st Som. LI. begins

HIMALAYA was shelled this morning from 8.15 to 10.15 a.m. with from 120 to 150 4.2 shells and a few 5.9's. The line of the road received most attention, but nearly all the trenches were shelled, and considerable damage was done. I had 6 casualties.

If I had not put one Coy. in the Cave, I should have suffered more heavily as the trench vacated by them was badly knocked about.

At present I have nearly the whole Battn. in the Cave.

I do not consider this position to be particularly safe now and casualties are likely to be regular.

The only protection is the Cave.

It is impossible to avoid all movement as there is no through trench communication. All orderlies etc. have to come over the top.

The whole position is under observation by balloons and the greater part under direct observation.

All day working parties found by the Battn. here and the men attached to the tunnellers have to move in view of the enemy. Also there is too much movement along the road of lorries, wagons, etc.

17/8/17. (Signed) For B.G.C., 11th Infantry Brigade.

11th Infantry Brigade - Daily Intelligence Summary

17/8/17 - 18/8/17

OPERATIONS

Our own

A standing patrol was out again last night in front of I.31/2. The only thing heard was a working party about I.32.a.0.3.

A patrol went from W Sap at 1 a.m. and lay out in a shell hole about I.31.b.8.3. until 2.30 a.m. With the exception of the above working party nothing was noticed.

A patrol left E Sap at 11 p.m. and proceeded S. along enemy wire and came in at 7 Sap. Enemy was reported to be in very good condition. Nothing seen or heard of enemy.

At 1.0 a.m. patrol left B Sap and examined enemy line I.25.d.4.8. to I.25.d.20.85. Progress was made along W. bank of Ravine until a notice board, possibly artillery mark, painted slate colour was reached. near by were found some consolidated shell holes linked up with earth to form a parados. Position thickly wired. "Very" lights were fired from I.25.d.3.8. Sounds of working in the ravine were heard. Party returned at 2.45 a.m. to FINGER at I.25.d.0.9.

ARTILLERY

Our own and the Enemy's was normal throughout the 24 hours.

MACHINE GUNS

Our Own

Machine guns on our left report. During the daytime the two guns in NOEUX WOOD kept very close watch on enemy's position south of river. At about 10 a.m. a man was seen in post approximately I.25.b.3.0. and was immediately fired on and was seen to drop.

Enemy

The Enemy Machine Gun in the Sap at I.31.d.92.88. was again active and swept our parapets during the night. The gun appears to be of the light class. Enemy Machine Gun traversed H and G post.- long range fire.

Between 9.0 p.m. and 12.0 p.m. WELFORD S. of JOHNSON was swept with fire at intervals.

TRENCH MORTARS

Our Own

The following trenches and positions were fired on by our Stokes Mortars during the night.

1. ARCHIE TR. in I.25.d. at 11.30 p.m. and 12.30 p.m. also again at 4 a.m.

2. Suspected M.G. positions at I.25.0.35.75. Whilst firing on this target enemy put up green lights but as far as we could ascertain nothing happened in consequence.

3. during the night salvoes were fired on DEVILS TRENCH from I.31.b.90.70. to I.32.c.2.5.40. Sentries report that during these operations at enemy stand-to, a Machine Gun which was in section in front of Y Sap was put out of action by us.

4. An enemy T.M. (light) opened fire from I.32.c.25.35. Immediate retaliation was given on this mortar. No firing came from this position during the remainder.

5. Bursts of fire were put on enemy front line in I.32.c. at 1.a.m. Enemy put up several red lights.

Enemy

In reply to our T.M. fire at 4.15 a.m. a double green light was fired and the enemy minewerfer opend fire on SCABBARD between 1.45 and 3.45 a.m.

Minnies 2 and 5 intermittently shelled SCABBARD, WRIST and ELBOW.

INTELLIGENCE

Two Bosches were observed laying wires about I.32.a.8.6. at 11.30 a.m. The stationary Kite Balloon over JIGSAW WOOD was again observed signalling at 9 p.m. last night.

6 observation balloons were up most of the day between VITRY Church and BOIS DU SART. One was observed signalling as follows:-

A | ATIHYOTE.
B | BITTAT III
C | EST
D | II TTT U II
E.C. ZI/EI FFL 74II
F A TT T O/X

What appears to have been a snipers loophole is suspected about 150 yds from N.E. corner of RAVINE in ANGEL.

At 9.10 a.m. a German was observed walking along ANGEL towards DEVILS returning 9.30 a.m. He waqs fired on by snipers and disappeared at N.E. corner of Ravine.

Enemy heavy and light Machine Guns were spotted at I.25.d.8.0.

18/8/17. (Signed) For Brigade Major, 11th Infantry Brigade.

11th Infantry Brigade - Daily Intelligence Summary

for 24 hours ending 6 a.m. 19.9.17.

OPERATIONS

A standing patrol of 1 Officer and 11 other ranks went out from I.31/1 to about 20 Yards in front of our wire and remained there until dawn.

Patrols went out from O.2/7 and O.2/6 to examine our wire and no man's land.

A patrol went out from O.2/6 and visited the posts and trenches of the Battalion on the Right.

In no case were any Germans seen and no work was heard.

A patrol of 1 N.C.O. and 1 Man was out yesterday morning from 4.0 a.m. to 12 midday. They took up position about 40 yds. in front of our wire at I.32.c.06.35. No enemy movement was observed. Enemy Machine Guns were seen to fire at our Aircraft from the neighbourhood of GUN TRENCH. The wire in fron of ARROW TRENCH is barbed concertina and strong.

ARTILLERY

Our own

ANGEL TRENCH was shelled between 12.0 noon and 1 p.m.

Intermittent shelling of the enemy front line and back area during the day and night.

Our Trench Mortars fired salvoes at 9.0 p.m. and 4 a.m.

Enemy

Very active from 6.30 a.m. to 10.0 a.m. and again from 10.15 a.m. to 10.0 p.m. During this time the trench North of the river were shelled with a gun of large calibre. About 12 5.9 shells fell in the vicinity of the Northern end of WELFORD RESERVE during the afternoon. The bank near Left Battalion Hd. Qrs. was searched during this period. CRUMP TRENCH was shelled during the evening. The single Railway Arch was shelled intermittently all day.

The night was quiet. At 4.30 a.m. about 10 77 m.m. shells were fired at O.2/8. Only one direct hit was obtained. They came from approximately East of the BOIS DES AUBEPINES.

MACHINE GUNS

Enemy

During the night H Post was swept periodically by M.G. fire. Direction not ascertained.

Between 8.30 p.m. and 9.0 p.m. I25/2 to I.25/3 were traversed.

TRENCH MORTARS

Our Own

Shoots were carried out on the following positions during the night.

1. At irregular intervals salvoes and bursts were fired on enemy front line at I.25.d.75.35. I.31.b.90.70. and I.32.c.20.30.

2. At 4.0 a.m. an organised shoot was carried out by all guns on the German front line. This shoot lasted three minutes during which time 152 rounds were fired. The machine guns co-operated in the operation.

Enemy

The T.M. previously located at I.26.c.55.40. was active during the night on RIFLE TRENCH.

A few medium T.M's. fell between our front and Reserve Lines about I.31.c.55.95. in retaliation for our T.M. activity.

Retaliation was given for our firing, which was heavier than usual.

Enemy T.M. was located at I.32.c.20.25. This gun was very active in retaliation.

INTELLIGENCE

An enemy working party was observed at I.32.d.57.63. at 5.0 a.m. this morning, they were dispersed by Lewis Gun fire and later a man was observed being carried away apparently on a stretcher.

At 1.0 a.m. an enemy patrol was observed in No Man's Land about I.31.d.90.95. They were fired on by Lewis Guns and dispersed.

At 1.20 a.m. yesterday morning a German was killed immediately in front of P.1. Post. A sentry on the Post hearing suspicious sounds in the grass immediately in rear of his Post turned round and saw a German about 12 feet away kneeling in the grass. He ordered him to put up his hands, the German began handling his rifle so the sentry shot him through the head. He had evidently been wading through the marsh as he was wet up to his waist and was wearing no equipment. He was thoroughly searched and his effects forwarded to Division. A patrol was sent out after this to reconnoitre the ground, which was reported all clear.

New work has been observed on ARCHIE TRENCH I.25.d.15.95. also on bridge at the RED HOUSE.

Many "Very" lights were sent up from DEVILS TRENCH between CIGAR COPSE and BOIS DES AUBEPINES. With the assistance of these lights a sniper was active against our carrying and wiring parties from a shell hole about O.2.b.0.9. The flash of his rifle was fired at.

At "Stand down" three Germans were seen returning towards BOIS DES AUBEPINES about O.2.b.25.65. They were fired at.

At 8.40 p.m. a very dark red double light was sent up by enemy from JIGSAW WOOD; this was followed after 2 minutes by a "Very" light (white). Nothing was observed to follow.

General

Between 1 a.m. and 2 a.m. an enemy searchlight as observed from behind DELBAR WOOD.

Enemy trench mortars were active between 2.15 a.m. and 3.30 a.m. on BRIDOON LANE and the ORCHARD. At 6 p.m. yesterday a fire was observed on the W. side of PLOUVAIN.

19th Aug. 1917. (Signed) For B.G.C., 11th Infantry Brigade.

11th Infantry Brigade - Daily Intelligence Summary

19/8/17 - 20/8/17

OPERATIONS

Our own

An Officers patrol left Sap O.2/6 at 10.20 p.m. with the intention of locating the approximate lines of German Posts in front of BOIS DES AUBEPINES and finding out if the ground was clear for putting out a covering party well in adavance of our wiring parties. The patrol crossed in front of TWIN COPSES about O.2.b.0.4. then moved towards BOIS DES AUBEPINES; after a short distance it was fired on from apparently a Post in front of DEVILS TRENCH after waiting some minutes patrol moved to left towards junction of TWIN TRENCH and O.2/6. It was again fired on from a different shell hole in advance of DEVILS TRENCH and on the North slope of the Ridge. The patrol returned at 11.15 p.m. The enemy appeared to be very alert and frequent lights were sent up.

A standing patrol went out from I.31/1 as soon as it was dark about 20 yds. in front of our wire. No Germans were seen and nothing was heard.

ARTILLERY

Enemy

Enemy Artillery quiet by day more active by night. 7 a.m. several 77 .m. shells fell near BRIDOON, the parapet being hit twice. 9 p.m. 77 m.m. shells fell along the line of ARROW SUPPORT and derelict trench behind it. 9.30 p.m. about 30 5.9's fell along I.31/1 and CHAIN SUPPORT. 3 direct hits were obtained. About 15 shells were fired again on this area at 10.15 p.m.

The enemy shelled our back areas by day but was quiet on the front line. About 8.45 p.m. the enemy shelled SCABBARD SUPPORT, RIFLE SUPPORT with 4.2 Hows. At about 9.15 p.m. the enemy shelled our front and support lines woth Hows. and 5.9's.

MACHINE GUNS

Our Own

Our M.G's in G. and H. Posts fired 5,000 rounds at enemy tracks from 10.0 p.m. to 12 m/n and 1 a.m. to 2 a.m.

Enemy

Enemy M.G's were active.

TRENCH MORTARS

Our Own

During the night the usual harassing fire was kept up on the German front line, special attention being paid to portions of the line in I.31.b.

Enemy

Light Trench mortar activity was below normal and was only employed in retaliation for our fire.

INTELLIGENCE

At 7 a.m. timber as seen being carried along CARTRIDGE at intervals of 10 minutes.

At 10.0 a.m. a German was seen to get out of DEVILS TRENCH at about I.32.c.95.05. and walk to a shell hole in rear; he was shot at as he stepped into the shell hole.

A German was seen looking out of DEVILS TRENCH at about O.2.b.08.85.; he was also fired at.

Timber was seen being carried in DEVILS North of BIT LANE. A German was seen coming out of a house on the Southern side of PELVES and was fired on.

At 7.40 p.m. a "Very" Light was sent up from ARROW South of BIT LANE.

Enemy's Trench Mortars and Machine Guns were active at intervals throughout the night. An old enemy M.G. emplacement was found about 20 yds. in front of Y Sap. Boxes of German M.G. belts were found in it.

At 7.30 p.m. signalling was observed from about I.15.c.1.2. lasting half-an-hour. These signals appeared to be answered from I.28.b.4.5. (QUARRY WOOD).

A daylight patrol went out as far as I.31.b.8.8. About 20 yds. away on the road appears to be an enemy listening post, new earth having been thrown up. The enemy wire is very thick in front of here.

A working party was observed at 4.45 a.m. this morning about I.32.d.62.67. It was dispersed by Lewis Gun fire. Work was proceeding at this point about the same time yesterday and it is thought that this may be a party which works all night until dawn.

Miscellaneous

When enemy shells fell short near CIGAR COPSE and DOIS DES AUBEPINES, Green flares were at once put up in quick succession.

Snipers

Snipers were active throughout the night opposite the Right Coy. Right Sub Sector, against wiring parties. Flashes were observed from 3 places and fired on.

20th August, 1917. (Signed) For B.G.C., 11th Infantry Brigade.

11th Infantry Brigade - Daily Intelligence Summary

20/8/17 - 21/8/17

OPERATIONS

An Officers Patrol went out from O.2/8 at midnight towards ARROW S. of BIT LANE. It reached a point about 40 yds. W. of this trench. Sounds of work in the trench were heard as though poles were being driven in. Voices were also heard. The sounds afterwards ceased and "Very" lights were directed towards the patrol.

Sounds of work in DEVIL were also heard.

The patrol noticed on the ground tracks of enemy patrol which had apparently been out earlier on the same night.

A patrol left Y Sap at about 12 midnight and proceeded towards the enemy's wire and returned via K Sap. No signs of enemy were seen.

ARTILLERY

Our own

A fire was caused by our guns North of JIGSAW WOOD.

Enemy

Quiet on the front system. The vicinity of I.31.c.20.05. was shelled with 5.9's at about 9.15 p.m. and again at midnight. A few shells were fired into MONCHY about 6 a.m. and again at 1.50 p.m.

About 5.30 a.m. BRIDOON was shelled by 77 m.m. guns with H.E. and a few lachrymatory shells.

About 10.30 p.m. he shelled the area of the front system spasmodically.

MACHINE GUNS

Our Own

Our M.G's fired as follows last night :- No. 8 gun in MUSKET RESERVE fired on enemy Battalion Head Quarters in I.27.a. No. 11 gun in H Post fired on enemy tracks in I.33.a and I.32.b. 2 Guns in G Post fired on shell holes E. of CARTRIDGE TRENCH in co-operation with Artillery gas shell bombardment between 5.30 a.m. and 5.45 a.m. The gun at No. 9 Post fired N. of KEELING COPSE during the bombardment. Gun at G Post fired on tracks S. of PELVES AND I.33.a.

Enemy

Enemy M.G's were active during the night; they swept H Post - RIFLE TRENCH N of LONE AVENUE is swept night and day periodically at the places where it is shallow.

TRENCH MORTARS

Our Own

Selected points and suspected M.G. and T.M. positions were fired on at different times during the night.

Enemy

Enemy T.M's from 1 a.m. to 5 a.m. were active on I.31/5. These were firing from about I.26.c.55.40.

A T.M. fired about 20 rounds at our wiring parties in front of TWIN Trench. First shots went well over our trench but the range was gradually shortened. The Artillery was informed and our field guns opened fire. The T.M. did not fire again. The flash of this T.M. was observed in line with the West end of CIGAR COPSE and our Post at the Eastern end of O.2/6.

Snipers

Enemy snipers were quiet on the right and did not fire at our working parties.

INTELLIGENCE

At 5.50 p.m. signalling was observed from FRESNES. At 9.50 p.m. signalling was observed from between HATCHET and JIGSAW WOODS.

Enemy captive balloon was observed signalling behind DELBAR WOOD at 9.0 p.m. Signalling was observed from direction of PELVES during the night.

A hostile post has been located at I.25.d.20.90. movement was observed here yesterday, only the steel helmets of the men being visible.

A sniper firing from about I.25.d.9.5. last night was silenced by Lewis Gun fire.

An enemy wiring party was heard opposite V Sap about 11.0 p.m. Lewis Gun fire was opened on to it.

A German was seen walking from DEVILS TRENCH to a shell hole behind it about O.2.b.1.9. and was fired at.

Enemy was heard working on DEVILS about I.32.a.7.2. most of the night.

Aircraft

At 7 a.m. an E.A. flew over our lines, dropped 3 bombs in the direction of MONCHY and then returned.

21/8/17. (Signed) For B.G.C., 11th Infantry Brigade.

11th Infantry Brigade - Daily Intelligence Summary

21/8/17 - 22/8/17

OPERATIONS

Our own

At 9.40 p.m. a patrol of 1 Offr. and 3 men went out from the right Post at O.2.a.8.7. to locate if possible enemy snipers opposite our right between CIGAR COPSE and the BOIS DES AUBERPINES who had been sniping our wiring parties the night before. No snipers were active and none located. This patrol reported two enemy working parties.

1. Digging in front of Battn. on our right (Exact position could not be located).

2. Wiring with stakes in fron of CIGAR COPSE. Hammering could be distinctly heard.

A patrol of 1 Offr. and 1 N.C.O. went out in front of our wire at about I.31/2 to reconnoitre portion of ARROW TRENCH North of BIT LANE. There was no sound of movement detected. This portion of ARROW appears to be badly knocked about and was very hard to recognise.

A patrol went out from Z Sap about 11.0 p.m. last night. They heard the enemy working on his trench and wire, immediately sent back for a Lewis Gun to open fire. No further work was heard after the Lewis Gun had opened fire.

Enemy

About 11.30 p.m. a strong enemy working party was reported in DEVILS TRENCH about I.32.a.0.2. A "Very" Light was sent up which by accident was a red one. Directly after this, work ceased and was not heard again.

ARTILLERY

Our own

Our Artillery carried out what appeared to be a gas shell bombardment between 6.30 p.m. and 7.30 p.m. in the neighbourhood of JIGSAW WOOD.

Enemy

Enemy Artillery activity was above normal. At about 8.15 p.m. the enemy shelled with 4.2" and 77 m.m., SNAFFLE, Northern end of BRIDOON and MONCHY. The Artillery lifted from SNAFFLE to BRIDOON and from BRIDOON to MONCHY. On enemy shells falling short enemy sent up 1 single green light and range was lengthened.

At 3.45 a.m. enemy shelled our right front line and CHAIN SUPPORT. Two direct hits were obtained on O.2/8. A single green light was again sent up, when range was lengthened.

A light barrage of 4.2" Hows. lasting about 3 minutes was put down on the Support and Reserve and communication trenches of our left Bn at 8.30 p.m. last night and 5.15 a.m. this morning. This has occurred the last two days and it seems likely the enemy is trying to catch working parties.

TRENCH MORTARS

Our Own

During the night shoots were carried out against suspected M.G. positions. Heavy retaliation waqs given by us (for enemy gas bombardment) on DEVILS and ARROW TRENCHES.

During the night enemy minenwerfer put over a quantity of gas bombs in 3 successive bombardments between O.2.a.15.95. and I.31.b.5.1. The gas felt fairly strong on the right of this area. Gas N.C.O's were unable to detect the identity of the gas by smell there was not sufficient to take samples.

Enemy trench mortars were very active last evening at "Stand to" firing on our left Coy. from about I.26.c.55.40. Between 2 a.m. and 2.30 a.m. this morning lachrymatory trench mortars firing from above positions, fell between our front line and SCABBARD SUPPORT. It is believed that of about 250 of these mortars a few contained phosgene.

At 11 p.m. 2.0 a.m. and 3.15 a.m. light T.M's fired quantities of gas shells on the right and left of our fron line. The gas drifted along our lines but was not heavy enought to compel us to put on respiratiors.

MACHINE GUNS

Our Own

Our M.G's fired indirect on to enemy tracks in I.33.a. and b. and I.32.b. and on the Battalion H.Qrs. in I.27.a.

The M.G's on our left report their right gun in ROEUX WOOD silenced a hostile M.G. firing from approx I.25.d.65.80. at 9.45 p.m.

Enemy

Enemy M.G's were more active that usual and swept reserve lines and HAPPY VALLEY during the night.

INTELLIGENCE

A good deal of movement can be seen in enemy trenches in front of BOIS DES AUBERPINES.

Most of the Minnie fire reported above came from the direction of CIGAR COPSE.

1 enemy M.G. was firing from behind DEVIL about I.32.a.1.4.; an emplacement can be seen at this point by daylight.

Between 8 and 9 p.m. last evening Artillery were firing short, the shells pitching in front of DEVILS TRENCH. A green light was put up and the range was lengthened.

AT 5.40 p.m. after shelling by our Hows. a fire was observed towards left edge of JIGSAW WOOD and at 7.40 p.m. large volumes of smoke were observed from same place. At 7.40 p.m. large volume of pink smoke was observed from left of BOIS DU SART.

3 enemy searchlights were observed from behind JIGSAW during the night.

A patrol which went out from V Sap returned through W Sap, reports that the enemy appears to be working on the line of shell holes about I.31.d.9.8. It is not yet known whether trench is being dug here or not.

22/8/17. (Signed) For B.G.C., 11th Infantry Brigade.

11th Infantry Brigade - Daily Intelligence Summary

22/8/17 - 23/8/17

OPERATIONS

Our own

Patrols were out in front of I.31/4 and I.31/3 during the night. No signs of the enemy were seen, but a shell hole was discovered about 40 yds. from our wire in front of I.31/3 which had obviously lately been occupied by the enemy.

ARTILLERY

Our own

Our Artillery carried out an organised shoot on DEVILS TRENCH between 4.0 p.m. and 5.0p.m. Trench Mortars fired on same objectives between 9.45 and 10 p.m.

Enemy

Activity below normal. At 3.45 p.m. and again at 4.15 p.m. a light barrage was put down in the neighbourhood of MUSKET and BAYONET TRENCH lasting about 5 minutes.

During the night some shells fell in the neighbourhood of I.31.c.20.05. At 5 a.m. about 20 77 m.m. shells fell near MONCHY and ORCHARD RESERVE.

TRENCH MORTARS

Our Own

A shoot was carried out against enemy M.G. emplacements at I.32.a.00.25. with good results. At 4.0 a.m. a shoot on DEVILS and ARROW TRENCHES in I.32.c. was carried out, in retaliation for light Trench Mortar fire on our working party.

Enemy

Medium T.M's were fired at Right Coy., Right Sub-Sector at 1.55 a.m. but no damage was done.

Enemy Trench Mortar in I.26.c. fired occasionally during the day, the shells falling between our front line and SCABBARD SUPPORT, and also occasionally during the night.

MACHINE GUNS

Our Own

Our M.G's at G. H. and No. 8 position fired 6,000 rounds indirect on to enemy tracks and Headquarters.

Enemy

Enemy M.G's were active during the night against wiring parties on the right of the Right Sub-Sector.

INTELLIGENCE

An enemy field battery was observed firing from behind a small wood on the left of JIGSAW WOOD. From the flashes it appears to be QUARRY WOOD.

New wire was observed from O.2.a.9.8. to O.2.b.05.70. The enemy seems to be working in his trench and saps between CIGAR COPSE and BOIS DES AUBEPINES.

An enemy sniper was observed firing from a tree in O.3.a.6.8. (approx).

A man wearing a soft cap with a white band round it was seen by CIGAR COPSE.

A good deal of enemy movement was seen at I.21.b.15.75; this spot will be kept under observation with a view to informing the Artillery.

From CHAIN SUPPORT a M.G. position was located in a house in PELVES. This house is at the foot of a big red brick factory chimney, which has been broken off half way down by shell fire.

When our T.M's were firing this morning a green light was sent up from DEVIL. This was followed by another Green light bursting into two. No action followed.

During the bombardment of DEVILS Trench between 4 and 5 p.m. Several of the enemy in front of I.31/4 appear to have been wounded, as shouts and groans were heard coming from the enemy trench.

At 5.15 a.m. scattered parties of the enemy were seen in the neighbourhood of JIGSAW WOOD, KEELING COPSE and the SAND PIT,; apparently working parties returning after a nights toil. Lewis Gun fire was opened up on to the nearer parties.

At 4.0 a.m. enemy put up 4 Green lights about O.2/8 apparently for "lengthen range" as some of his shells were falling on his own trench.

At 6.30 p.m. yesterday 22nd inst., a pigeon was seen flying in an Easterly direction over our lines towards PELVES. The pigeon was watched and lost sight of when it got past PELVES.

23/8/17. (Signed) For B.G.C., 11th Infantry Brigade.

11th Infantry Brigade - Daily Intelligence Summary

23/8/17 - 24/8/17

OPERATIONS

Our own

A patrol of 1 Offr. and 1 N.C.O. went out from I.31.d.9.5. at 9.15 p.m. to examine ARROW. The enemy were extremely active with lights which made movement difficult. They got close to trench, when a light was sent up a short way to their front. They waited and listened and heard the enemy talking but there were no sounds of work and he was not wiring in front of DEVIL. No wire was found in front of ARROW. They then proceeded Northwards along the trench and about 15 yds. from it. Several lights were fired at their direction; the patrol returned to the point fron where it had started. No enemy patrol was encountered.

An Officers patrol left V Sap at 1.30 a.m. and patrolled No Man's Land returning by W Sap. All was quiet. The enemy fired 3 Very lights (white) in rapid succession which fell a few feet from Y Saphead.

Enemy

The enemy was exceptionally quiet. He traversed with a M.G. about 2 a.m. along our left front line.

ARTILLERY

Our own

During the night there was intermittent fire on enemy's front and support lines. On the whole our Artillery was unusually quiet.

Enemy

About 3.30 a.m. enemy shelled the vicinity of MONCHY with medium sized shells, probably 4.2's about 40 rounds were fired.

TRENCH MORTARS

Our own

During the night salvoes were fired on DEVILS TRENCH between I.31.b.8.7. and I.32.a.0.3. where M.G's were active.

Salvoes were fired on ARROW TRENCH I.32.c.10.45. which was reported to be occupied.

MACHINE GUNS

Our Own

Our M.G's at G Post and No. 8 Position fired 4,000 rounds on enemy tracks and Battalion Head Quarteers in I.27.a.

INTELLIGENCE

The enemy appears to have done a good deal of work on his parapet opposite the extreme right.

The M.G. at I.31.b.9.6. fired at an aeroplane at 2.30 p.m.

An Helio was signalling in GUN TRENCH at 3.12 p.m.

3 Germans were seen at 5.5 p.m. standing outside TREE TRENCH at I.33.c.9.6. for 5 minutes.

No enemy balloons were up during the day.

At 9.52 p.m. what appeared to be a Gas Alarm was heard from enemy lines North of the RIVER SCARPE followed by coloured lights and barrage being put down on our front line (N. of the RIVER).

Signalling with a red lamp was observed from direction of PLUVAIN at 9.45 p.m. and between 11.30 p.m. and 12.10 a.m. The message was not intercepted.

At 9.30 p.m. a fixed red light was observed in front of JIGSAW WOOD the light moved slightly backwards and forwards until 10.30 p.m.

Our M.G's were active throughout the night. The enemy at 3.15 a.m. fired 24 rounds of medium size T.M. Bombs which fell around I.31/5 (4th Div. Trench Map) about 20 yds. short of our front line trench.

At 5.30 a.m. 3 Germans were seen walking from the direction of KEELING COPSE towards CARTRIDGE TRENCH. They wore great coats and did not carry rifles. When fired on they disappeared into a trench.

24/8/17. (Signed) For B.G.C., 11th Infantry Brigade.

11th Infantry Brigade - Daily Intelligence Summary

24/8/17 - 25/8/17

OPERATIONS

Our own

An officer and N.C.O. left our trenches on patrol about I.31.d.8.4. and went due East. After going about 90 - 100 yds. they found two shell holes which showed recent signs of occupation. An enemy working party was heard. On advancing further thay found a part of four wiring: fire was not opened owing to our wiring parties being in that vicinity.

A patrol of 1 Offr. and 1 N.C.O. left W Sap at 12 m/n and went East 100 yds. towards DEVILS TRENCH, a German wiring party was distinctly heard. Patrol went forward another 20 yds. and found themselves very near another party which must have been out as a covering party. This party was discovered by one of them coughing. Patrol laid there some time until about 1.10 a.m. Patrol then returned and heard another party South of W Sap. Patrol entered W Sap about 1.30 a.m. and opened fire on hostile patrol and working party.

Another patrol of 1 Off. and 1 O.R. left X Sap at 11.20 p.m. and proceeded South East. Patrol went as far as the enemy's wire in front of DEVILS TRENCH and found that the wire consisted of two rows of plain concertina wire, with barbed wire twisted into it. The grass between the enemy's wire and his trench has been cut. DEVILS TRENCH appears to be a wide trench and blown in in parts. None of the enemy was seen in the trench. Patrol returned through Y Sap at 12.15 a.m.

Patrol of 1 Offr. 2 O.R. left Y Sap at 12 m/n and crawled towards enemy Sap at I.31.b.8.7.: when within 20 yds. of the Sap three of the enemy were seen standing on the parapet of the Sap. Two bombs were thrown at them.

Patrol then wheeled South for about 40 yds. when it again turned East and proceeded about 80 yds. where it encountered a German patrol of 9 advancing towards our lines. Our patrol was not strong enought to fight so it returned to our lines by Y Sap at 1.15 a.m. when Lewis Gun fire was opened on the enemy's patrol.

ARTILLERY

Enemy

Enemy Artillery was active from 6 to 8 a.m. against MONCHY. About 9 a.m. 30 5.9s fell in the vicinity of I.31.c.20.05. About 10 p.m. 10.15 and 10.30 p.m. field guns put a light barrage on front and support line from I.35.d.95.05. to I.35.d.75.70.

MONCHY was shelled with 5.9's and 4.2's all day and night. On our own front the enemy Artillery has been very quiet. About 9.45 p.m. about 30 77 m.m. shells were fired about I.31/4.

TRENCH MORTARS

Our Own

The following points were fired on by our mortars during the night. Suspected M.G. position in DEVILS TRENCH at I.31.b.99.45. Enemy front line at I.32.c.45.25.

Enemy

The enemy retaliated on our positions for our fire on the first mentioned targets. When firing on the second target, the enemy put up a green light which broke into three. This was repeated 3 times, as far as we could ascertain nothing happended in consequence.

A few rounds were fired at 9.30 p.m. and 5.30 a.m. on SNAFFLE. A few rounds were fired at N. TWIN COPSE at 5.15 a.m. At 5.30 a.m. they were active against the Left Coy. Obtaining one direct hit on CHAIN SUPPORT.

MACHINE GUNS

Enemy M.G's were extremely active against the Right Coy. Right Sub-Sector interfering considerably with the wiring parties.

INTELLIGENCE

The MG's mentioned above are reported to have been firing from O.2.a.90.90. and I.32.c.65.30. The M.G. emplacement reported previously at I.31.b.9.6 has been covered over with brown earth and more wire put in front of it. Throughout the day Germans were seen to walk in pairs and singly from JIGSAW WOOD in the direction of HAMBLAIN.

The usual signalling took palce during the night from JIGSAW WOOD.

2 Germans were seen in DEVIL during the day and were fired on by our snipers.

At 3.15 p.m. about 20 Germans were seen on the South side of PELVES. Arrangements have been made to inform the Artillery if they are seen again.

When our trench mortars were firing the enemy sent up a green light bursting tnot two; this was repeated twice bu no action followed.

It was observed that as soon as our Stokes Gun opened fire, the enemy sent up a light which burst into green, this appeared to be answered by one white light from the Support and then their Artillery opend fire. Several White Very light were fired at 10 p.m. last night East of JIGSAW WOOD.

Signalling was also seen from the same point.

3 Germans wearing shrapnel helmets were observed in DEVILS TRENCH at 9 a.m. the 24th at I.32.a.1½.0.

E.A's were observed over our line at 9 a.m.

At various times during the afternoon a heliograph was observed signalling from a tree in VICTORIA COPSE.

From BRIDOON a party of the enemy was seen at I.21.a.75.35. walking about. It is thought that they live in this vicinity.

25/8/17. (Signed) For B.G.C., 11th Infantry Brigade.

11th Infantry Brigade - Daily Intelligence Summary

25/8/17 - 26/8/17

OPERATIONS

Our own

A patrol of 1 Offr. and 1. O.R. left our trenches about I.32.c.0.0. They crawled to within 30 yds. of the enemy's wire and heard a party at work. About 10 appeared to be wiring and another party could be seen digging on the parapet. At 10.30 p.m. some shells and T.M. Bombs were fired near our wiring parties on the left of the Left Coy. Right Sub-Sector. One red light bursting into two was sent up from the enemy's trench and the range was shortened and soon afterwards another red light breaking into four was sent up and the shelling ceased. At the same time two whistles were head and everybody disappeared into the trench. The patrol stayed for about another hour but no movement was seen in the trench. An enemy covering party was observed at about 11 p.m. on the right of the patrol.

At "stand-to" a patrol of 1 Offr. and 1 N.C.O. went out from about I.31.d.8.4 to find out if the enemy was working. Hostile wiring parties were seen. The patrol returned and Lewis Guns opened fire with good effect.

An Officers patrol went across the gap and saw no enemy; the next Battalions Post was visited.

At 11.15 p.m. a hostile working party at about O.2.b.25.75 was successfully dealt with by our Lewis Guns.

A patrol of 1 Offr. and 20 O.R. left X Sap at 1.30 a.m. and advanced to within 20 yds. of the enemy's wire. The wire consists of two rows of plain concertina wire with barbed wire twisted in. No sign of work was observed in the enemy's line but voices were heard. The patrol returned via V Sap at 2.15 a.m.

Another Officers patrol left V Sap at 9 p.m. and proceeded for about 100 yds. in an EASTERLY direction stopping at intervals to listen. It then moved North for 150 yds. The enemy was inactive. Patrol returned via W Sap at 10.30 p.m.

Enemy

During the day his snipers were active. His trench mortars were livelier than usual. The enemy fired 20 Rifle Grenades about I.31/2. At intervals during the day the enemy fired a number of light Trench Mortar bombs between SCABBARD SUPPORT and the front line.

ARTILLERY

Enemy

Enemy Artillery was more active at 2.30 p.m. Twenty 5.9's fell around trench junction I.31.c.20.05. and this place received attention at intervals during the night. Field guns shelled the Right of the Right Sub-Sector at 9 p.m. and harassed wiring parties of the left Coy. of the Right Sub-Sector at 10.30 p.m.

MONCHY was shelled off and on throughout the period.

About 3.30 p.m. H Post was lightly shelled.

TRENCH MORTARS

Our Own

During the night shoots were carried out on the following targets,
1. M.G. position at I 31.b.95.65. This gun did not fire again during the remainder of the night.
2. DEVILS TRENCH at I.32.c.23.40.

Enemy

Hostile T.M's were extremely active throughout the day. The Right Coy. of the Right Sub-Sector received most attention.

A Medium Trench mortar was particularly active at 6.30 p.m. ; it was easily visible by its smoke and was firing from I.33.c.2.3.

MACHINE GUNS

Our Own

Our guns at G, H and P.9 positions fired on enemy tracks N. of KEELING COPSE and S. of PELVES.

Enemy

Enemy M.G's swept H and G Post during the night - some of our Infantry troops were hit in LANCER LANE in H.36.c and d. The gun was apparantly firing from PELVES.

Hostile M.G's were again very active especially against the Right Coy. of the Right Sub-Sector.

INTELLIGENCE

Several small parties were seen at 5.30 p.m. coming down the road at I.22.d.5.5., at which point they entered a trench.

A small party was seen working at I.28.b.2.8.

3 men wearing helmets were seen in DEVIL about I.32.c.5.3. they were fired on and disappeared. A few Germans wearing soft caps with peaks were seen in DEVIL at 10.50.

An enemy working party was seen at about 2.30 p.m. from I.26.b.15.00. to I.26.b.0.5. Our Artillery were informed.

Several Germans were seen during the day near PELVES.

When the enemy shelled our front line some shells dropped short, a rocket bursting into two red lights was then fired from DEVILS TRENCH. The firing then stopped for a few moments, then continued, the range was then considerably increased.

The usual signals observed with a red lamp in JIGSAW WOOD.

An enemy's working party was observed in front of DEVILS TRENCH at I.31.b.95.35 about 9.50 p.m. The Artillery were informed and six rounds were fired at them. This working party was not again heard or seen.

At 2.20 a.m. a train was heard behind the enemy's line.

Two pigeons flew over our line at 7 a.m. flying towards MONCHY.

Machine Guns on our left report. During the day movement was seen in ANGEL TRENCH. Several of the enemy were fired at but managed to escape. One man, observed climbing over the parados was fired at and seen to fall over the parados. A strict watch was kept on this spot but he was not seen again; it is presumed he was hit.

Digging was observed at junction of ANGEL and ARCHIE Trenches as much fresh earth was thrown over the parapet.

26th August, 1917. (Signed) For B.G.C., 11th Infantry Brigade.

ARTILLERY (Continued)

Unusual enemy activity during the afternoon. At 2.40 p.m. the enemy shelled LONE LANE - H Post - ORANGE AVENUE - LIME TRENCH - one direct hit was obtained on H Post and two direct hits were obtained on ORANGE AVENUE.

MONCHY was shelled with 5.9's or 8" at about 3 p.m.

11th Infantry Brigade - Daily Intelligence Summary

26/8/17 - 27/8/17

OPERATIONS

Our own

A patrol of 1 Offr. and 1. O.R. left X sap at 8 a.m. and crawled 50 yds. N.E. to I.31.b.7.5. working round South to I.31.b.8.4. From this position sounds of someone picking and talking were heard about I.31.b.9.4. The patrol remained stationary at I.31.b.8.4. observing until 9.15 a.m. when it returned to our line via X Sap.

A patrol of 2 Offrs. left Y Sap at 5 p.m. for the purpose of inspecting our wire round Y Sap. When the patrol got out to the wire it heard picking in front so crawled forward and discovered that the enemy were working underneath the tall telegraph pole at I.31.b.7.7. It is suspected that the enemy are making an observation post here. The patrol listened and observed for a few minutes and then returned to our lines and obtained some rifle grenades. It then went out again to our wire and fired 11 rifle grenades at the pole but it is not known with what effect. Patrol came in at 6.10 p.m.

ARTILLERY

Our own

Our artillery fired on the Heavy T.M. at I.32.c.7.3. at 10.45 a.m. This T.M. has not fired since.

Enemy

The enemy shelled MONCHY with gas shells between 5.20 a.m. and 5.40 a.m. Otherwise quiet.

Enemy Artillery activity below normal on our front. A few rounds were fired on our back areas during the day. About 6 T.M. shells were fired at our front line at junction of CURB ALLEY and HALBERD TRENCH. About 20 pineapple bombs were fired on our trench at 2 a.m. and again at 4.15 a.m.

TRENCH MORTARS

Our Own

During the night a shoot was carried out on bank I.32.a.05.00 - I.32.a.05.05 where a M.G. was suspected.

Retaliation was given for enemy T.M. fire on our emplacement in CURLY TRENCH which silenced the enemy for the remainder of the night.

Enemy

MACHINE GUNS

Our Own

M.G's at P.9. and H Post fired on enemy tracks etc., during the night.

Enemy

Enemy M.G's were active and swept the vicinity of H Post during the night.

INTELLIGENCE

Hostile snipers were more active than usual.

8 hostile Balloons were in the air about 8.15 a.m.

There was considerable movemement in and about PELVES. Our artillery were informed.

Men were occasionally seen walking along CARTRIDGE TRENCH at I.32.b.3.2. They were not wearing steel helmets. The trench appears to be very shallow for some distance on either side of this point. At about 5.30 a.m. 26th, a pigeon flew from the enemy line towards ours and then swerved and flew off in the direction of JIGSAW WOOD.

A number of pigeons were let loose from the enemy line front line at 8.0 p.m. It is reported one flew along our front line and was fired on and hit. It could not be brought in as it fell in the enemy's wire.

At 9.20 a.m. 2 men left the JIGSAW WOOD and disappeared over the ridge to the N.

2 men walking over the open got into a trench in the vicinity of PARK WORK.

A small body of men was observed on the road about I.22.d.1.0. 2 minutes later our shrapnel was observed to burst over the spot.

Between 9.0 p.m. and 11.0 p.m. a lamp was observed signalling from behind JUNCTION COPSE.

28/8/17. (Signed) For B.G.C., 11th Infantry Brigade.

11th Infantry Brigade - Daily Intelligence Summary

27/8/17 - 28/8/17

OPERATIONS

Our own

Our standing patrol N. of T. Sap report nothing seen or heard. An Officers patrol left W Sap at 12 m/n and adavanced in a S.E. direction for about 30 yds. from our wire. They then lay down and listened. The weather and wind were very unfavourable for hearing anything so the patrol pushed on for another 20 yds. They remained out until 12.50 a.m. but nothing was heard or seen.

Another Officer patrol left Y Sap at 1 a.m. for the purpose of examining the enemy's work near the tall telegraph pole as ordered. The patrol crawled out towards the supspected Post but no sound of working was heard. Two of the enemy were seen by the telegraph post that is leaning over. Sounds of whistling were heard from this direction but owing to the very bad weather and intense darkness, no enemy's work could be observed. The patrol returnd at 1.45 a.m.

ARTILLERY

Our own

Hrassing fire until midnight; very quiet afterwards.

Enemy

Two salvoes of 5.9 were fired between RIFLE SUPPORT and MUSKET TRENCH at 5.0 a.m. and at junction of LONE LANE and RIFLE at 5.20 a.m.

Enemy shelled with H.E. at 3.30 to 3.50 p.m. or our right front, ORCHARD TRENCH was shelled between 4.30 and 4.50 a.m.

There was a marked inactivity on the part of the enemy's Artillery.

At noon 15 shells fell on TWIN TRENCH, MONCHY and also RIFLE TRENCH were shelled at intervals during the day.

TRENCH MORTARS

Our Own

At 12.15 p.m. a shoot was carried out on road at I.31.b.75.70 where enemy was suspected to be wworking. It is thought that excellent results were obtained as wood was thrown into the air.

During the night shoots were carried out on CIGAR COPSE.

Shoots were carried out on M.G. position at I.32.a.15.05. and I.32.c.65.30.

Enemy

Enemy fired on TWIN COPSES.

7 rounds were fired at our No. 2 Lewis Gun post (O.2.a.95.65.) which had just been firing. Direct hits were made on parapet and traverse causing collapse of both. Gun and personnel were undamaged.

MACHINE GUNS

Our Own

Out M.Gs. from H. Post and P.9 position fired intermittently throughout the night at enemy tracks and roads.

Enemy

Enemy M.Gs. swept H Post at intervals during the night and were also very actively sweeping the Left Sub-Sector.

INTELLIGENCE

Between 3 and 4 p.m. four of the enemy were observed proceeding from one dugout to another with what seemed to be cooking utensils at I.23.a.8.6. to I.28.a.8.7.

At 8.55 p.m. 2 Germans were seen to leave DEVILS TRENCH at BIT LANE. They were fired on.

About 5 men were observed at work draining in DEVILS TRENCH about I.31.b.90.70. Trench boards were seen being carried near this point.

At 9.30 a.m. and again at 12.30 p.m. a party of about 20 men were seen to emerge from DELBAR WOOD.

Small parties of the enemy were continually seen moving about in the open in twos and threes about I.28.d.2.7. They appeared from behind the ridge and disappeared near PARK WORK early this morning.

28/8/17. (Signed) For B.G.C., 11th Infantry Brigade.

11th Infantry Brigade - Daily Intelligence Summary

28/8/17 - 29/8/16

OPERATIONS

Our own

A patrol of 3 O.R. left V Sap at 11 p.m. and remained out for an hour. No enemy movement was seen and the enemy did not appear to be doing any work.

A patrol under an Officer left our front line at I.31.b.5.7. at 1.45 a.m. and worked towards the enemy Sap opposite Y Sap. Whistling was heard and lights were put up apparently from this enemy sap. No enemy were encountered and no work appeared to be in progress.

Enemy

Nil

ARTILLERY

Our own

Normal during the day; by night bursts of harassing fire were fired on back areas and enemy tracks.

Enemy

Very few rounds were fired on this front.

Trench mortars were fairly active during the 24 hours. One was distinctly seen firing and a bearing was taken from Battalion Head Quarters in BAYONET TRENCH. The magnetic reading was 109 degrees. The exact spot can easily be seen and was pointed out to the Artillery Officer. A few rounds were fired but weather conditions did not appear to favour accurate or consistent shooting.

TRENCH MORTARS

During the night the following shoots were carried out:-

On enemy front line I.32.c.2.7. to I.32.c.2.5.
On enemy working party in ARROW TRENCH I.32.c.25.30.

MACHINE GUNS

Our Own

Our M.G's fired 6,000 rounds on enemy tracks as follows:-

No. P.7 and 8 ..... On I.22.b. No P.9 ..... On I.26.b. and Battn. H.Q.

Enemy

An enemy M.G. traversed LANCER LANE and H Post throughout the night.

INTELLIGENCE

A white signalling lamp was observed to be used in the direction of DELBAR WOOD at 11 p.m. No message could be picked up. At 11.30 p.m. what appeared to be an enemy S.A.A. dump was on fire behind HAUSA WOOD.

At "Stand down" this morning the enemy sent over T.M's of a very large calibre. They dropped in the vicinity of CHAIN SUPPORT.

Considerable movement of enemy moving in twos and threes has been observed in the direction of QUARRY WOOD.

At 10.45 p.m. a brilliant flare was seen in the direction of DEVILS TRENCH opposite junction of HARNESS and HALBERD. Nothing unusual followed. White lights were sent up every time the T.M. fired (vide enemy's Artillery). Obviously this T.M. had a man registering for it. This man's position appeared to be on the high ground opposite the Left of the Right Sub-Sector.

29/8/17. (Signed) For Lt. Col. Commdg. 11th Inf. Bde.

11th Infantry Brigade - Supplementary Daily Intelligence Summary

28/8/17 - 29/8/16

OPERATIONS

Our own

An Officers patrol left T Sap in I.31/1 at 10 p.m. and proceeded 100 yds. down BIT LANE, they then turned N.W. and proceeded 50 yds. parallel to ARROW TRENCH, a clear view of which could be obtained owing to the moonlight. A M.G. then opened fire from about I.31.d.95.50 (N. end of ARROW). The patrol remained in a shell hole for a quarter of an hour during which time 3 Very lights were fired from 2 sentry posts in ARROW. One post was just S. of BIT LANE. No work or wiring was going on, on the trench.

A patrol of 1 Offr., 1 N.C.O. and 3 men left ARROW Sap at 12.30 a.m. and proceeded N.W. along ARROW. At I.32.c.35.10 a cough and talking was heard. Patrol moved closer and heard a party digging. One coil of barbed concertina is out almost on the parapet of ARROW. Men could not be seen in the trench which is deep. A patrol of 4 men were observed to come out of the trench and disappeared in an Easterly direction.

Patrol then moved further along and found enemy digging up to I.32.c.25.20. They returned to our lines E. of BRIDOON ALLEY. The T.M.'s were informed of the position of this working party and fired 30 rounds in three bursts. The Lewis Guns cooperated firing 3 magazines enfilade fire.

ARTILLERY

Enemy

Enemy occasionally shelled MONCHY, BRIDOON, CHAIN SUPPORT and RIFLE SUPPORT.

TRENCH MORTARS

Enemy

5.0 to 5.5 p.m. 10 rounds heavy Minnie on right Coy H.Q. Right Sub-Sector, and BRIDOON.

9.20 p.m. Minnie 2 fired 20 rounds on BRIDOON T.M. emplacement. Our Artillery retaliation was successful. This Minnie did not fire again.

INTELLIGENCE

Between 8.30 and 9.30 a.m. and again at 6.0 p.m. a party of 6 to 10 Germans were seen grouped together at the foot of a telegraph pole on the ridge about 500 yds. left of HAUSA WOOD.

At 9.30 a.m. a party of 4 men were see working in DEVILS Tr. about I.32.a.10.05. Thry were fired on by one of our snipers and 1 hit.

Between 9 a.m. and 1 p.m. large parties of the enemy were seen moving backwards and forwards along ARTILLERY LANE E. of HATCHET WOOD. At about 2.30 a.m. an enemy transport wagon was seen on this road in I.34.a. It disappeared into HATCHET WOOD.

29/8/17. (Signed) For Lt. Col. Commanding 11th Infantry Brigade.

11th Infantry Brigade - Daily Intelligence Summary

29/8/17 - 30/8/17

OPERATIONS

Our own

At 1.10 a.m. an Officers patrol left T Sap to ascertain whether the enemy was working on ARROW TRENCH. Work was in progress about 50 yds. S. of BIT LANE.

At 2.20 a.m. a patrol of 6 O.R. left I.31/1 junction with LINK ALLEY. The advanced 150 yds. due E. and found the enemy occupying ARROW TRENCH as Very Lights were fired from 3 different places in it. They then turned S.E. towards BIT lane and returned to our lines at O.2/8 near BRIDOON ALLEY. The enemy was not working on ARROW at that hour.

The standing patrol N. of T Sap report no sound or movement on the part of the enemy.

A patrol of 1 Offr. and 2 O.R. left W. Sap at 11.50 p.m. Patrol went about 30 yds. in front of the Sap and listened but heard nothing, and then made a right incline for about 50 yds. stopping at intervals to listen. Digging was heard from what appeared to be I.32.c.25.85. in DEVILS TRENCH. No German patrols were encountered and no movement could be seen anywhere. Patrol returned by W Sap at 12.40 a.m.

ARTILLERY

Our own

ANGELS and DEVILS TRENCH shelled with 16 pdrs. at intervals during the day especially between 10 and 11 p.m.

Harassing fire carried out on the BOIS DE AUBERPINES between 9.15 and 10.50 p.m.

Enemy

MONCHY was shelled with 5.9 during the day; about 10% of the shells failed to explode.

RIFLE and CHAIN SUPPORT also I.31/1 and O.2/8 were registered on with 77 c.m's by day.

During the morning MUSKET RESERVE was fired on with 5.9.

TRENCH MORTARS

Our Own

During the night our mortars fired on working party at I.32.a.10.05.

Enemy

A Minnie was very active on SNAFFLE from ARROW SAP to BRIDOON ALLEY and along the latter between 7.30 a.m. and 8.30 a.m. and again from 7.30 p.m. to 7.45 p.m. Two bursts were fired at 5.45 a.m.

About 7.0 p.m. enemy fire 14 rounds of medium T.M. at our wire in fron of I.31/1.

Between 11 p.m. and 2 a.m. a gain active. A direct hit was obtained on junction of CHAIN SUPPORT and LINK ALLEY. Two mortars fell in our wire near T Sap.

MACHINE GUNS

M.G. activity on both sides normal.

INTELLIGENCE

At about 4 p.m. a party was observed deepening ANGEL TRENCH about I.31.b.8.7.

About 10 a.m. a large party of the enemy was seen carrying timber near HAUSA WOOD.

A white Very light bursting into 2 stars was the signal for enemy T.M's to lengthen range.

Enemy snipers were active during the day.

The smoke of an engine was seen behind HATCHET WOOD.

On the morning of the 28th upwards of a dozen white stakes 8 to 10 ft high were observed in front of JIGSAW WOOD. They had disappeared by the morning of the 29th.

On the evening of the 28th between 10 and 11 p.m. bursts of golden spray similar to the bursting of a P bomb were observed at intervals in the enemy's trenches along the whole front, they also appeard to be fired N. of the SCARPE.

Two of the enemy were seen carring jugs or tins from one point to another in PARK WORK at 12.30 p.m.

CHAIN SUPPORT was heavily minenwerfered at 3 p.m.

Two men could be seen working in DEVILS TRENCH between 1 p.m. and 5 p.m. near telegraph pole at about I.32.c.2½.5. They were wearing steel helmets and capes. These men were observed from CHAIN TRENCH. At 8.40 p.m. about 6 of the enemy were seen in front of their wire at I.32.a.9.4. They were fired on by Lewis Gunners. Rifle Grenades were also fired. The party was dispersed. It was impossible to see if any loss was inflicted. They were not seen again. Our Lewis Gunners swept the enemy wire near this point during the night.

It would appear that two red lights is the signal for their Trench Mortars to open fire as two red lights were seen on two occassions during the night and their trench mortars fired immediately afterwards in each case.

30/8/17. (Signed) For Lieut. Colonel, Commanding 11th Infantry Brigade.

11th Infantry Brigade - Daily Intelligence Summary

30/8/17 - 31/8/17

OPERATIONS

Our own

A patrol consisting of 1 Sgt. and 2 O.R. left W Sap and moved due East from the Sap about 30 yds. and laid down and listened. After about 5 mins. they moved S.E. along the bank of the Valley for about 25 yds. and came across a shelter consisting of corrugated iron. A circular Type. The top was covered with earth 18" thick. This was concealed by growing grass. A track led back from this shelter towards the enemy's line. The grass around this shelter was beaten down. There was no other sign of recent occupation. A seat was made all around and a man could sit there in a stooping position. This is probably a sniping post as a number of shots lately have come from about this point. No enemy's patrols were met and no sounds of work were heard in enemy's lines. Patrol returned at 1.10 a.m.

A patrol of 1 N.C.O. and 2 O.R. left X Sap at 2.0 a.m. Patrol went East for about 30 yds then worked North towards enemy's Sap opposite Y Sap. Some rifle grenades were fired from enemy's Sap. No enemy patrols were encountered. Patrol returned by Y Sap at 2.45 a.m.

ARTILLERY

Our own

Between 3.0 and 4.0 p.m. DEVILS TRENCH was repeatedly shelled North of the SCARPE our heavy artillery fired with effect on a working party near DELBAR WOOD.

Enemy

MONCHY was shelled during the day with shells of various calibres.

Enemy shelled MUSKET and CURB SWITCH (North) trenches at 4.30 a.m. with 4.2's.

Enemy shelled front line in SNAFFLE TRENCH at 4.30 a.m. with same calibre shells.

MACHINE GUNS

Our Own

Or M.G's fired harassing fire during the night.

Enemy

An enemy M.G. fired during the night. The shots appeared to come from the direction of BOIS DES AUBEPINES, otherwise they were comparatively inactive.

INTELLIGENCE

At 11.55 a.m. a German in a soft cap was observed walking down DEVILS TRENCH from N. to S. at a point just N of CIGAR COPSE, carrying dugout timber.

Several men in steel helmets were seen about the same point by our observers. A man taken for an Officer owing to peaked cap and gold braid on epaulettes was directing the work.

Our snipers hit a man behind DEVILS TRENCH at 500 yds. range. He fell and two others went out to him but left him. It is presumed he was killed.

The sap opposite Y Sap appeared to be garrisoned fairly strongly as Very lights and rifle grenades appear to come from this direction in fair numbers.

One Offr. and 2 men were seen in DEVILS TRENCH at 11 a.m. The Offr. was viewing our lines with field glasses. The men were pointing out something to him. They were fired on and then disappeared.

Aircraft on both sides was below normal.

The flash of an enemy T.M. was observed in DEVILS TRENCH at about I.32.a.00.50. Transport was heard during the night apparently from the direction of JIGSAW WOOD.

31st August 1917. (Signed) for Lt. Col., Commanding 11th Infantry Brigade.